<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Our World in Data - Data Insights</title>
        <description>Bite-sized insights on how the world is changing, written by our team</description>
        <link>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/</link>
        <atom:link href="https://ourworldindata.org/atom-data-insights.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>Family is very important to people around the world</title>
            <guid>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/family-is-very-important-to-people-around-the-world</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Bastian Herre</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img
            src="https://ourworldindata.org/images/published/how-important-family-is-to-people-in-life-mobile.png" /><br><br>Most people agree that family is very important, no matter where they live.<br><br>Using data from the European Values Study and World Values Survey, the chart shows that a large majority of people worldwide declare family to be important in their lives. This share is above 80% in every country <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/how-important-family-is-to-people-in-life?country=CAN~HKG~LVA~NIC~NLD~LTU">except six</a>.<br><br>Only a small percentage of people say they find family “not very important” or “not important at all”.<br><br>Despite our disagreements, we should remember how much people across countries and cultures agree on what truly matters to them.<br><br><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/how-important-family-is-to-people-in-life">Explore this data</a> →]]>
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Coal power is dying in Western Europe</title>
            <guid>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/coal-power-is-dying-in-western-europe</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Hannah Ritchie</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img
            src="https://ourworldindata.org/images/published/coal-europe-mobile.png" /><br><br>Coal dominated Europe's electricity mix over the 20th century, but it is quickly dying in many countries in the 21st.<br><br>The chart shows the share of electricity that comes from coal for a range of countries in Western Europe. The data comes from <a href="https://ember-climate.org/">Ember</a>.<br><br>Transitioning away from coal has helped <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/co2?stackMode=relative&time=2000..latest&facet=none&country=GBR~IRL~ESP~PRT~GRC~DNK~NLD~DEU&Gas+or+Warming=CO%E2%82%82&Accounting=Territorial&Fuel+or+Land+Use+Change=All+fossil+emissions&Count=Per+country">reduce carbon emissions</a> and <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/explorers/air-pollution?time=1990..latest&facet=entity&uniformYAxis=0&country=GBR~IRL~ESP~DNK~DEU~GRC~NLD~PRT~ITA&Pollutant=Nitrogen+oxides+%28NOx%29&Sector=From+all+sectors+%28Total%29&Per+capita=false">local air pollutants</a>.<br><br><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/share-electricity-coal">Explore the data</a> →]]>
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>Extreme poverty, though lower than in the past, is still very high in Sub-Saharan Africa</title>
            <guid>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/extreme-poverty-though-vastly-reduced-is-still-very-high-in-sub-saharan-africa</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Pablo Arriagada</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img
            src="https://ourworldindata.org/images/published/share-of-population-in-extreme-poverty-ssa-eap-mobile_1350.png" /><br><br>The United Nations’ first Sustainable Development Goal is to <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/sdgs/no-poverty">“end poverty in all its forms everywhere”</a> by 2030. The world is still very far away from this goal.<br><br>The data from the World Bank shows that in 1990, 55% of the population in Sub-Saharan Africa and 65% in East Asia and the Pacific lived in these conditions — broadly similar figures. But the most recent figures were 37% in Sub-Saharan Africa and 1% in East Asia and the Pacific.<br><br>The United Nations focuses on “extreme poverty” in its Sustainable Development Goals agenda. They define this as living with less than $2.15 per day. This figure represents what $2.15 could buy you in the United States in 2017 prices; it is adjusted for inflation and cost of living differences between countries.<br><br><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/share-of-population-in-extreme-poverty?tab=chart&facet=none&country=Sub-Saharan+Africa+%28PIP%29~East+Asia+and+Pacific+%28PIP%29">Explore this data</a> →]]>
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <item>
            <title>Human rights have improved in all world regions over the last century</title>
            <guid>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/human-rights-have-improved-in-all-world-regions-over-the-last-century</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Bastian Herre</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img
            src="https://ourworldindata.org/images/published/human-rights-index-vdem-mobile.png" /><br><br>Human rights are much better protected in all world regions than a century ago, according to data by <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/vdem-human-rights-data">Varieties of Democracy</a>.<br><br>This recently updated chart shows an index <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/vdem-human-rights-data">that captures human rights</a>. The index ranges from 0 (least rights) to 1 (most). As you can see, every world region scored significantly higher in 2023 than 100 years ago.<br><br>Although progress has not been steady, and there have been setbacks — including in recent years — the overall improvements have been substantial. These trends remain when <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/human-rights-index-population-weighted?time=1923..latest">giving more weight to countries with larger populations</a>.<br><br>While progress has been made in all world regions, there are still big disparities across them, with Africa and Asia lagging behind. And the strong protections on other continents show that further global progress is possible.<br><br><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/human-rights-index-vdem?tab=chart&time=1900..latest&country=OWID_ASI~OWID_AFR~OWID_EUR~OWID_NAM~OWID_SAM~OWID_OCE">Explore this data</a> →]]>
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Solar panel prices have fallen by around 20% every time global capacity doubled</title>
            <guid>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/solar-panel-prices-have-fallen-by-around-20-every-time-global-capacity-doubled</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Hannah Ritchie</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img
            src="https://ourworldindata.org/images/published/solar-learning-curve-mobile.png" /><br><br>One of the most transformative changes in technology over the last few decades has been the massive drop in the cost of clean energy. Solar photovoltaic costs have fallen by 90% in the last decade, onshore wind by 70%, and batteries by more than 90%.<br><br>These technologies have followed a “learning curve” called Wright’s Law. This states that the cost of technology falls consistently as the cumulative production of that technology increases.<br><br>The chart shows the perfect example of this for solar power. This data comes from the International Renewable Agency, Greg Nemet, and Doyne Farmer & François Lafond.<br><br>On the horizontal axis, we have the cumulative installed capacity of solar panels, and on the vertical axis, the cost. Both are measured on logarithmic scales, and the trend follows a straight line. That means the fall in cost has been <em>exponential</em>.<br><br>Costs have fallen by around 20% every time the global cumulative capacity doubles. Over four decades, solar power has transformed from one of the most expensive electricity sources to the cheapest in many countries.<br><br><a href="https://ourworldindata.org/learning-curve">Learning curves: What does it mean for a technology to follow Wright’s Law?</a> →]]>
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>The price of lighting has dropped over 99.9% since 1700</title>
            <guid>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/the-price-of-lighting-has-dropped-over-999-since-1700</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Esteban Ortiz-Ospina</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img
            src="https://ourworldindata.org/images/published/price-lighting-mobile_1350.png" /><br><br>In the last two centuries, the price of lighting has decreased drastically.<br><br>You can see this in the chart, which plots historical data from <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Roger-Fouquet/publication/241752411_The_Long_Run_Demand_for_Lighting_Elasticities_and_Rebound_Effects_in_Different_Phases_of_Economic_Development/links/0a85e52fb80f72624c000000/The-Long-Run-Demand-for-Lighting-Elasticities-and-Rebound-Effects-in-Different-Phases-of-Economic-Development.pdf">Roger Fouquet and Peter Pearson</a>. To allow for comparisons over time, the data is adjusted for inflation and expressed in prices for the year 2000.<br><br>In the 1300s, one million lumen-hours — a standard lighting measure — would have cost around £40,800 in 2000 prices. By 2006, this had fallen to £2.90, a 14,000-fold decline.<br><br>Innovations in lighting appliances, fuels, infrastructures, and institutions during the 19th and 20th centuries made this progress possible.<br><br>To put this in perspective, consider that a standard 100-watt incandescent light bulb today can emit about 1,700 lumens. Therefore, running one such bulb for 24 hours would produce about 50,000 lumen-hours. That means that 1 million lumen-hours today would require continuously keeping a standard 100-watt incandescent bulb on for about 25 days. Achieving the same amount of light with candles would require burning more than 100 candles every day for that period.<br><br>Most people today take the ability to switch on a light at night for granted. But those who live or have lived without artificial light can appreciate how important it is.]]>
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title>Homicide rates have declined dramatically over the centuries</title>
            <guid>https://ourworldindata.org/data-insights/homicide-rates-have-declined-dramatically-over-the-centuries</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2024 07:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <dc:creator>Bastian Herre</dc:creator>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<img
            src="https://ourworldindata.org/images/published/homicide-rates-across-western-europe-mobile_850.png" /><br /><br>It
        is hard to imagine just how violent the past was.<br /><br />The chart shows that in the
        13th and 14th centuries, based on data from researcher Manuel Eisner, homicide rates across
        Western Europe were higher than 10 murders per 100,000 people in a year. In Italy, the rate
        was as high as 70 murders per 100,000 people.<br /><br />Since then, murder rates have
        fallen significantly across these countries. According to data from WHO’s Mortality
        Database, their homicide rate is now around 1 murder per 100,000 people — less than a tenth
        of what it used to be.<br /><br />Despite these improvements, homicides remain a common <a
            href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/annual-number-of-deaths-by-cause">cause of
            death</a> globally and are even a <a
            href="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/share-of-deaths-from-homicide">leading
            cause</a> in some countries. But significant and lasting reductions in violence between
        people are possible.]]>
            </content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
